<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2017-12-31T23:45:15-08:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/</id>
<subtitle>I review books I listen to while waiting in traffic.
</subtitle>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<entry>
<title>Annihilation, Jeff VanderMeer</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/annihilation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Annihilation, Jeff VanderMeer" />
<published>2017-12-28T02:32:20-08:00</published>
<updated>2017-12-28T02:32:20-08:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/annihilation</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/annihilation/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-8&quot;&gt;Score: 8&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-nope&quot;&gt;Spoilers? Nope.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-sure-to-check-out-my-scoring-scale-to-see-what-the-score-means&quot;&gt;Be sure to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/scoring-scale&quot;&gt;Scoring Scale&lt;/a&gt; to see what the score means.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annihilation by Jeff VanderMeer is a fantastic read, and I would recommend it to anyone.  I am relatively new to the bio-punk genre, and I’m not even sure if this sits squarely in it, but I’ve been loving it. And not just for the genre, the book itself was suspenseful journey into…well, it was definitely something, though I have no idea what. It’s weird, mysterious, and gives a sense of ominous doom that makes it hard to walk away from. It also left me thinking after I was done. A total win in my book. (Full disclosure, I just realized that they’re making this into a movie in 2018 as I was writing this post so, now I feel kind of silly reviewing something that a lot of people may actually watch.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s start of with the basic premise: there is a mysterious Area, aptly named Area X, where a similarly mysterious government agency called the Southern Reach send expeditions from which no one returns…except those who do! That’s right! Sometimes, people come back from this secret Area X, but when they do, they’re changed. They don’t remember anything, they’re lucid, but never really able to engage with the normal world.  For some reason, people keep going into Area X to plumb it’s depths, but to no avail. The area is transitioning into some other type of ecosystem, but no one knows what - only that it’s expanding…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story follows the journey of an all female expedition, made up of a Psychologist, an Anthropologist, a Surveyor, a Linguist, and a Biologist. Our story follows the Biologist and her observations of the dangerous and mysterious world of Area X.  The world is transforming nature into something that seems both human and far from it. It’s got a strong, stoic lead, and at one point there’s a creepy person-eyed dolphin. Just that sentence checks a lot of boxes for me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the most fascinating aspects of the book is that the Biologist is just weird. It was actually somewhat off-putting as I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story follows the Biologist as she treks through Area X, all the while recalling the life before hand that brought her there. The descriptions of Area X are visceral depictions of a gray and brown wintry marshland. In it, everything seems as it should be on it’s surface, but it’s permeated by a profound wrongness. Each character has to struggle with a different type of discomfort with the surroundings. And all of them struggle except for the Biologist.  She, unlike the others has always longed for the wilderness. Throughout her back story we learn of her escapes from her “real life” into small havens of wilderness that pop up in the interstices of society: an neglected pool or an abandoned and overgrown lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fascinating aspects of the book is that the Biologist is just weird. It was actually somewhat off-putting as I read. She describes her life prior to her expedition as a sepia-toned fumbling to fit in among other humans. More than anything she simply wants to escape and go observe the wonder of nature, and she laments the quickly disappearing wildernesses of the world. It’s as if in every scene where she has to interact with other humans, she is the only one who can see that the wilderness is calling, but it’s also disappearing from view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VanderMeer uses these back stories to fill in plot holes, and at times they seem a bit contrived. For example, the Biologist describes difficulty getting along with her husband and a deeply strained marriage because, essentially, “he’s gregarious and I’m not.” I’m an introvert who struggles with mild/medium social anxiety, but even to me that seems like a slim excuse for the type of relationship they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/assets/img/annihilation_map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Annihilation Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, one character is haunted by dreams for most of his life, only to realize that the dreams were scenes from a movie and not to be feared. Being haunted by nightmares as a child seems like a pretty tragic experience, but VanderMeer just glosses over it. Later on, that fact helps explain the dreamlike quality of Area X, so it helps fill in a hole, but it feels a bit like it felt more like shorthand to get from point A to B instead actual character development. At times the interplay between the characters feels like VanderMeer is just saying, “just trust me, these people don’t get along”, or “this random back story doesn’t really develop the character, but it helps fill a plot gap, so I’ll just add it here.” It wasn’t bad, but I often found myself just needing to take characters at face value instead of really groking with their motivations and actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s clear that VanderMeer is painting a picture that’s meant to terrify. Human civilization is gone and past, though no one realizes it yet. Nature is alive and vital, though through a weird decay and transformation that leaves everything changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than the characters, what caught me about this book was the fact that central conflicts in the plot are actually terrifying in real life.  This story tries to explore the idea of a truly uncontrollable wilderness. While most of the worlds wilderness is receding, there is this one mysterious and unconquerable pocket…and it’s advancing.  That thought of a wilderness that’s out of our control constantly scratches at the back of your mind as you read. For me, what is so powerful about it is that we often forget that nature truly is uncontrollable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really hits close to home for me because of, well, the very premise of this blog: I work in a part of Seattle that’s really hard to get to via public transit. Taking the bus would add at least an hour my 2.5 hour daily commute, so I commute to and from work alone. But I do this with thousands of others. It’s easy to pretend that a society that is so nonchalant about the environment will never have to suffer the consequences, but nature is not something to be trifled with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In VanderMeer’s Area X, nature is master of all. Humans are at best, temporary visitors, only fit to be enfolded into the dangerous and mysterious world there. As the Biologist records her experience, it’s clear that VanderMeer is painting a picture that’s meant to terrify. Human civilization is gone and past, though no one realizes it yet. Nature is alive and vital, though through a weird decay and transformation that leaves everything changed.  No one has ever made it through that transformation and come out recognizable. It’s only the Biologist’s extreme oddness that makes her capable of staying aware as the transformations take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world like this, only change is possible. Most scifi asks us to look at our what we as a society are most afraid of and ask, “how bad could it get?”.  Annihilation asks us to look at a world where nature cannot be tamed and only complete and utter transformation gives a glimmer of a hope of survival.  It made me wonder how different that is from our world. What would it take to keep the globe from warming, to keep our oceans from becoming poisonous with debris, or to keep our forests and wilderness intact? Only a drastic change. And without it, nature will continue to advance, to strike back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a beautify look at some of our society’s deepest environmental fears, and it does this all in the middle of captivating imagery and a mysterious plot that kept me glued to my speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-id-recommend-this-to-anyone-even-if-you-dont-read-all-the-environmental-and-philosophical-stuff-into-it-that-i-do-its-a-suspenseful-story-that-is-artfully-done&quot;&gt;Recommendation: I’d recommend this to anyone. Even if you don’t read all the environmental and philosophical stuff into it that I do, it’s a suspenseful story that is artfully done.&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="Scifi" />
<category term="Biopunk" />
<category term="Jeff VanderMeer" />
<category term="Score 8" />
<summary>Score: 8</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Three Body Problem, Liu Cixin</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/three-body-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Body Problem, Liu Cixin" />
<published>2017-12-19T02:32:20-08:00</published>
<updated>2017-12-19T02:32:20-08:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/three-body-problem</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/three-body-problem/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-6&quot;&gt;Score 6&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-minor-spoilers&quot;&gt;Spoilers? Minor spoilers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-sure-to-check-out-my-scoring-scale-to-see-what-the-score-means&quot;&gt;Be sure to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/scoring-scale&quot;&gt;Scoring Scale&lt;/a&gt; to see what the score means.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three Body Problem was one of the weirder books I’ve read in a while, but it turned out to be a pretty good read. Three Body Problem is set in China and occurs mostly in the present day, though the back story stretches back to the Communist Revolution in the late 50’s and early 60’s. It begins with the story of a young girl whose Bourgeoisie parents and mentors are brutally tortured and killed in the Revolution, but she is able to escape to one of the last bastions of academic research: a military research facility in a remote mountain range.  At the start of the book, this all seems to be the main thread of the story, but it turns out to simply be back story for the real, present day story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part of Three Body Problem follows Wang Miao, an applied physicist working with nano-technologies. Through a series of seemingly miraculous events, Wang is conscripted into a secret government task-force investigating a secret society of academics called the Three Body Society. While on this task-force he discovers that the society is actually part of an elaborate plot to invite a refugee alien force to come colonize and conquer Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As I was reading, I constantly found myself asking, “is this a cultural thing, or just a convenient shorthand for the plot?”  I still have no idea, but that was part of the fun for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, it was a pretty slow start and in a location and culture that I know next to nothing about.  Another reason why it was so weird is that, toward the end, it tries to imagine a society that’s so vastly different than our own and a series of technologies so far fetched, that it was hard to wrap my head around it.  With all that said, the ultimate draw of the book for me was the utter strangeness of the plot, conflict, and characters.  I really enjoyed the book when everything was said and done, because it made me ask questions about Chinese culture, and also about the limits of physics and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons why this book stuck with me is because I just didn’t get it.  I didn’t get how the characters could all be so disillusioned with humanity. I didn’t get why characters were so respectful of their elders - there’s a moment where the Wang Miao goes to visit the mother of a deceased woman who he never met but had a crush on. Her mother was totally fine with some stranger/stalker showing up at her door and they strike up a friendship. There is a level of trust for strangers or acquaintances that was just so foreign to me. As I was reading, I constantly found myself asking, “is this a cultural thing, or just a convenient shorthand for the plot?”  I still have no idea, but that was part of the fun for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also intrigued how this story handled fear of environmental disaster. So many of the books that I’ve read lately who deal with that do so in totally different ways: the Expanse series talks about policy changes and space colonization, Annihilation and other bio-punk books talk about the horrors of nature striking back, but this…the world’s elites just give up and ask aliens to wipe us all out?  That is just so different from how I would ever think of dealing with that conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/assets/img/three-body-math.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three Body&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why I like this books - and I’m outing myself a bit hear - is that it deals with concepts from linear algebra.  I used to work as a pastor, but now I work as a data analyst (totally reasonable career pivot, huh?), and as such I’m needing to go back and revisit a lot of the math I neglected in my liberal arts degrees. As I was reading this, I was also working through some linear algebra textbooks. There is a part toward the end of the book where some of the characters take advantage of the multidimensional aspect of sub atomic particles as a weapon.  It is crazy, but as I was reading it, I was thinking through the different transformations that would need to happen to accomplish what the book talks about. It was fun to think, “would that actually be possible to apply pure mathematics to physical objects?” and “do current theories believe that subatomic particles are more than three dimensional?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not every day that a book makes me think of math, or that math makes me feel like I can relate to scifi better. Honestly, I’d probably have rated this story lower if I wasn’t literally doing linear algebra homework in between listening to the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The I rated this book as a 6 because, while it was a bit boring at the start, it was intriguing on so many levels.  I was fascinated by reading something Chinese for the first time. I was fascinated by the physics and math involved. I liked the characters, and by the time the story was done, I was really curious what would happen next. The characters were a bit hard for me to relate to, the conflict was coherent and complex but also a bit odd and sort of difficult to relate to.  I liked that aspect. I liked reading it and thinking, “why in the world would people act like this?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-read-it-its-worth-your-time-particularly-if-you-like-reading-stories-that-stretch-your-perspective&quot;&gt;Recommendation: read it. It’s worth your time. Particularly if you like reading stories that stretch your perspective.&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="scifi" />
<category term="Liu Cixin" />
<category term="Score 6" />
<summary>Score 6</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Stranger in a Strange Land, Robert Heinline</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/stranger-in-a-strange-land/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranger in a Strange Land, Robert Heinline" />
<published>2017-12-03T02:32:20-08:00</published>
<updated>2017-12-03T02:32:20-08:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/stranger-in-a-strange-land</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/stranger-in-a-strange-land/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-5&quot;&gt;Score: 5&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-yeah&quot;&gt;Spoilers? Yeah.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-the-book-is-56-years-old-so-who-cares&quot;&gt;(but the book is 56 years old, so who cares)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-sure-to-check-out-my-scoring-scale-to-see-what-the-score-means&quot;&gt;Be sure to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/scoring-scale&quot;&gt;Scoring Scale&lt;/a&gt; to see what the score means.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heinline is a legend. No one could take that from him, and I’m just a guy who listens to (scifi) books in my car, so he wins.  With that said, I didn’t really like this book.  One of the important things to remember is that my rating is subjective - really subjective.  I’m basically just putting my reactions out there, and this book didn’t do much for me.  The only reason why it was worth reading was to get a glimpse of what people were thinking in the late 50’s early 60’s.  And for that, it was fascinating. For one thing, that time period is a bit of a no-man’s land for me. I’m not huge into American history, so I know WWII was going on in the early 40’s, and the mid-late 60’s was all about hippies and Civil Rights. But between those? I guess that’s where you get Heinline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, there are some things that you just have to choose to stomach if you want to read this book. For one, it’s hopelessly sexist. As I was first reading it, I though, “Oh, Jill has a bit of spine, that’s good to see.” But as I read on, I realized that as soon as the plot was ready to make a man the main protagonist, Jill (and every other woman in the story) took a back seat as spunky, perky ornamentation for the scenes while the men did the talking. The sexism was rampant as far as only valuing the women for their physical features, but it was most upsetting that whenever the men were talking, the women just weren’t interested. They had no need for silly things like ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing you’d just need to stomach is that this book is written from the perspective of an upper-class white man. All others need not exist. That’s kind of what you get when you read Heinline. He uses science fiction as a medium to talk politics or philosophy, but he tends to do it sort of as a soap box.  It’s kind of why I love Heinline: he’s a true science fiction writer. He takes a concept or fear and extrapolates it into an imaginary world.  Ultimately, the conflict and plot in his stories are secondary to the dialogues that explain the ideas of interest. In this particular treaties, he’s interested in religion as a social power structure. I could imagine how that could have been an interesting concept at the time - the problem is that his take on that is that of a (probably) wealthy white man.  Social power structures and the assumptions behind them are very different to people of different walks of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/assets/img/stranger2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stranger Cover&quot; text-align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those two problems are enough for me to want to give the book a low score and make it a “don’t bother recommendation”, that’s really not the whole picture. While I didn’t like those things, I can recognize that, for his time, he was trying to give women more respect than they got in other stories.  I’ve only read a little bit from the 50’s and it’s not much different.  Also, he’s giving women full sexual freedom, which I’m sure was a revolutionary idea at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the main reason I didn’t care for the book was because I wasn’t particularly interested in his topic of choice. In Seattle 2017, religion as a social power structure isn’t particularly valid topic. I am an ordained minister. I have been through bible school at one of the most reputable religious universities in the region, I got a masters degree from Princeton Theological Seminary, and have worked as a protestant minister in churches since 2010 - and not once have I seen religious hold any significant social power over anyone. In the places I’ve lived, religion is just grasping at anything it can to get a seat at the table of social discourse. That’s why so many religious people become so angry and fanatically conservative: they want some proof that their beliefs, traditions, and habits actually matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a harsh critique of religion, and I’m a very religious person. I’ve got all kinds of ideas about why those things have happened, how to fix them, and all that. But, 1) that’s not what this blog is about, and 2) none of those ideas paid the bills, so I’ve moved on to paying gigs since…hence the whole working in Seattle and having the long commute that precipitated this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am explaining that to say that, in the 56 years since this book has been written, a lot has changed. For one, the Renaissance Man, Jubal Harshaw would probably have been imprisoned as a sex offender. For another, Valentine Michael Smith’s radical philosophy wouldn’t be that looked down on today in many circles. His free love commune could find safe haven somewhere in most countries, if not most cities in the United States. For that reason, the central conflict of the Stranger in a Strange Land simply don’t apply today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, there are a few things that I did like or learn from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-grok-or-not-to-grok&quot;&gt;To Grok or not to Grok&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually decided to read this book because a friend of mine at work mentioned how this book invented a word that has made it into the common vernacular. I didn’t know what she was talking about, but I later heard a data scientist podacst where someone used the word “grok” to explain some of the concepts a data scientist should probably master if they hope to excel in the field. I looked up where the word came to, and decided, why not give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grok means to understand a thing in it’s fullest. To get it to your bones. Like a part of who you are. In fact, that’s one of the main concepts of the book: that all things are one, and recognition of that fact brings a type of freedom transcends any other law. Anyone who can truly “grok” will become an Uberman, though everything groks whether they realize it or not. That concept sounds like a lot of what I read in seminary and I’d had enough of those debates in my early twenties. It felt like Heinline was just rehashing arguments I used to have outside my apartment, but he was doing it alone and fantasizing about sex at the same time. I wasn’t impressed. Though I really like the word and I now use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;picturing-an-uberman&quot;&gt;Picturing an Uberman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this book and then decided to finally watch the movie Lucy, with Scarlet Johansen. It was weird because her character followed a pretty similar arch to Michael in the story. Her ability to see and know everything reminded me a lot of him.  And the concept that “if we only awakened our inner potential, we’d be Gods!” is central to A Stranger in A Strange Land. It made me wonder whether that thread or belief is an influence of this book.  I’m not sure, but from now on, there’s no way I’m going to be able to hear that nonsense without thinking of Michael Valentine Smith, the Man from Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money-is-a-thing&quot;&gt;Money is a thing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great untapped areas of interest in this book was the role of money. In one of the (creepy) old covers, you can actually see the bowls of money in that are ever present in Michaels nest homes. Heinline quickly creates a conflict in his book where, due to various legal statues that had formed prior to Michaels birth, he qualified as the sole ruler and monarch of Mars, therefore inheriting a vast amount of wealth. This turned out to be preposterous because Mars was already owned by Martians, but the money had to belong to someone, so Michael got it. Since Michael comes from a Martian society with no money, the concept of money makes no sense to him and he has to struggle to learn it. Eventually, his disciples become absolute mavens at making money because of their Ubermensch powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point Michael explains that, unlike the Martians, money will always exist on earth.  Even in a society that has no need of it, there will always be a need because people will want things.  It is a somewhat preposterous idea, but it does say something about the world at the time: Heinline, for all of his imagination, could not imagine a world where communal living ultimately rules the day. Money exists, even if it serves no purpose to him. This point is telling to me because it proves itself: money is so powerful that you simply can’t get rid of it, even in Heinline’s science fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is a classic, and for that reason, people should read it. I just can’t imagine anyone who isn’t like me bothering.  With that said, the point of this whole blog is to give recommendations to other people who are stuck in their commutes way more than they should be.  For that reason, if you made it through Starship Troopers (which I really liked), or if - for some reason - you’re interested in the interplay between religion, money, and government as agents of social power…then go ahead and read A Stranger in a Strange Land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendation-i-guess-you-could-read-it-id-hate-to-meet-someone-under-the-age-of-60-who-actually-likes-it-though&quot;&gt;Recommendation: I guess you could read it. I’d hate to meet someone under the age of 60 who actually likes it though.&lt;/h2&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="scifi" />
<category term="Robert Heinline" />
<category term="Score 5" />
<summary>Score: 5</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Waking Gods, Sylvain Neuvel</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/waking-gods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waking Gods, Sylvain Neuvel" />
<published>2017-11-17T02:32:20-08:00</published>
<updated>2017-11-17T02:32:20-08:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/waking-gods</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/waking-gods/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-4&quot;&gt;Score: 4&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-why-bother&quot;&gt;Spoilers: Why bother?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-sure-to-check-out-my-scoring-scale-to-see-what-the-score-means&quot;&gt;Be sure to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/scoring-scale&quot;&gt;Scoring Scale&lt;/a&gt; to see what the score means.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waking Gods picks up pretty much where the prior book leaves off: giant robot needs to be reassembled, secret society put together to do the job, same cast of characters now just learning to use the machine.  The book was garbage and I regret reading it.  If you want to see why, just go read my take on &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}{% post_url 2017-11-02-sleeping-giants %}&quot;&gt;Sleeping Giants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll say this: some characters find out they had a kid whose really creepy. There’s more Pacific Rim ripoffs. The book ends with another out-of-nowhere twist that makes you go, “maybe the next one will be better than the last two.”  If I ever find out, it’s because the commute is really getting to me and I’m desperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no real review. I regret wasting my life listening to it, I don’t want to regret wasting my life writing a review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-dont-read-it--seriously-just-use-your-imagination-to-think-of-a-story-with-giant-robots-and-youll-have-a-better-time&quot;&gt;Recommendation: Don’t read it!  Seriously, just use your imagination to think of a story with giant robots and you’ll have a better time.&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="scifi" />
<category term="Sylvain Neuvel" />
<category term="Score 4" />
<category term="giant robots" />
<summary>Score: 4</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Sleeping Giants, Sylvain Neuvel</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/sleeping-giants/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sleeping Giants, Sylvain Neuvel" />
<published>2017-11-02T03:32:20-07:00</published>
<updated>2017-11-02T03:32:20-07:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/sleeping-giants</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/sleeping-giants/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-4&quot;&gt;Score: 4&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-yeah-totally&quot;&gt;Spoilers? Yeah, totally.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-sure-to-check-out-my-scoring-scale-to-see-what-the-score-means&quot;&gt;Be sure to check out my &lt;a href=&quot;{{site.baseurl}}/scoring-scale&quot;&gt;Scoring Scale&lt;/a&gt; to see what the score means.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sleeping giants was basically like watching Pacific Rim: it basically just dulls the fact that you don’t have anything better to do.  Honestly, this book wasn’t very good on so many levels, but there was just enough intriguing elements sprinkled throughout that I couldn’t justify not finishing it.  Basically, I was pretty happy to be done with it, until there was a surprise twist at the end that made me think, “why not give the next one a try?”  That is, in essence, what it takes for me to give something a score of 5: pretty much a waste of time, but it kept me from thinking about traffic on Friday afternoon, so, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book first caught my attention because of the initial suspense.  A young girl discovers a giant hand buried in the ground, only to grow up to become the scientist researching the giant hand. The hand is full of mysteries, and before long, a team of characters is assembled to get to the root of them. They find that the hand is part of a giant robot, and that the giant robot comes from an alien civilization.  From there on out it is a steady stream of small discoveries leading up to the realization that this robot is a weapon capable of immeasurable destruction. The similarity to Pacific Rim goes beyond the giant robots thing: the robot has to be manned by two pilots, cerebrally linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book reads like series of cliches strung together in the hopes of getting a movie deal.  Really, I listened to the whole thing thinking, “I should probably just stop, this is making me too angry.”  So often the plot reads like Sylvain just started writing and then made it up as he went.  For example, they find the robot, but (oh no!) the beings who made it have knees that don’t bend correctly.  So, when a pilot for the craft is discovered, he gets his legs smashed and the doctors build him legs that, you guessed it, bend backward. The plot line that brought this about are so out of keeping with all the characters involved, that it all feels contrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, it just seemed like Sylvain was bored and wanted to see if he could get this published. Either that, or it’s targeted at a much younger audience than me. But there is a fair amount of cursing and a bit of sex, so I don’t see how that would fly.  It all just seemed like  hodge podge of characters he found interesting, robots he though would be “cool”, and a thrown together plot that didn’t do much. One of the main characters is such a misfit for the whole story that I found myself wondering, “is this just Sylvain writing himself into a robot story?” There is a French Canadian linguist from Montreal who ultimately becomes the linchpin for piloting the giant craft. In the following book, he ends up having a mental break after killing one of his closest loved ones. He tinkers with building model ships to help recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was reading this book, I felt a bit guilty writing such a bad review, then I found Sylvain’s bio, and the whole thing made a lot more sense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sylvain Neuvel dropped out of high school at age 15. Along the way, he has been a journalist, worked in soil decontamination, sold ice cream in California, and peddled furniture across Canada. He received a Ph.D. in linguistics from the University of Chicago. He taught linguistics in India, and worked as a software engineer in Montreal. He is also a certified translator, though he wishes he were an astronaut. He likes to tinker, dabbles in robotics and is somewhat obsessed with Halloween. He absolutely loves toys; his girlfriend would have him believe that he has too many, so he writes about aliens and giant robots as a blatant excuse to build action figures (for his son, of course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, Sylvain wrote himself into a giant robot fantasy book.  That makes me both annoyed, and less guilty about writing about his books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really the only reason I read the second book was because it ends with someone who was dead reappearing on the other side of the world, alive and 4 years younger…and I like the voice actor who plays an aliens eyebrow-less ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-this-was-not-a-good-book-dont-read-it--unless-youd-like-to-see-a-guy-fantasize-about-being-a-hotshot-linguist-robot-pilot-dont-waste-your-time&quot;&gt;Recommendation: this was not a good book; don’t read it.  Unless you’d like to see a guy fantasize about being a hotshot linguist robot pilot, don’t waste your time.&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="scifi" />
<category term="Sylvain Neuvel" />
<category term="giant robots" />
<category term="Score 4" />
<summary>Score: 4</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Saturn Run, John Sandford</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/saturn-run/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saturn Run, John Sandford" />
<published>2017-10-20T03:32:20-07:00</published>
<updated>2017-10-20T03:32:20-07:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/reading/saturn-run</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/saturn-run/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;score-6&quot;&gt;Score: 6&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoilers-not-really&quot;&gt;Spoilers? Not really.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…post to come&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<author>
<name>Ben McCary</name>
</author>
<category term="scifi" />
<category term="John Sandford" />
<category term="realistic" />
<category term="space travel" />
<summary>Score: 6</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
